<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lambda on toddaas blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.toddaas.com/tags/lambda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Lambda on toddaas blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2024 05:10:21 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.toddaas.com/tags/lambda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>EC2 Autoscaling Warm Pools are very useful for looooooooong bootstrap times - Part 2</title>
      <link>https://blog.toddaas.com/posts/ec2_warm_pools_are_useful_part_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2024 05:10:21 +1000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.toddaas.com/posts/ec2_warm_pools_are_useful_part_2/</guid>
      <description>Overdue for Part 2 so thought I&amp;rsquo;d include some of my learnings along the way&amp;hellip;&#xA;Why Warm Pools again? Taking a step back to networking for a brief second and Warm pools from Part 1. Warm Pools are very useful for scaling network appliances, for example, a set of firewall appliances in an Autoscaling Group behind a Gateway Load Balancer (GWLB). This is simply because notoriously network appliances often take a long time to boot getting all their bootstrapping and inspection, IPS/IDS jazz together.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EC2 Autoscaling Warm Pools are very useful for looooooooong bootstrap times - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://blog.toddaas.com/posts/ec2_warm_pools_are_useful_part_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2023 05:10:21 +1000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.toddaas.com/posts/ec2_warm_pools_are_useful_part_1/</guid>
      <description>So whats the scenario? I came up against conflicting customer requirements of minimising the impact of long application bootstrap times in an autoscaling group partnered along side the requirement of keeping their standard barebones EC2 AMIs interchangable. Essentially the customer did not want to have to deal with the bloat or overheads of maintaining a specific prebaked application AMI alongside an image building solution like EC2 Image Builder or a third party solution like Hashicorp Packer.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
